Guide to the Mildred Davenport Dance Programs and Dance School Materials
Mildred Davenport dance programs and dance school materials
1934-1942
MS- P29
Davenport, Mildred, 1900-1990
0.3 linear feet (1 box and 1 oversize folder)
University of California, Irvine. Library. Special Collections and Archives. Irvine, California 92623-9557
This collection comprises dance programs, dance school materials, photographs, and ephemera documenting the early career of the Boston-based African-American dancer, dance instructor, and civic official Mildred Davenport. The bulk of this collection consists of dance programs and dance school materials. The collection also contains 29 photographs of Davenport, her students in various performances, and friends or individual students. Dance programs from 1925 to 1942 feature her solo performances and group performances with her students. The collection includes a complete run of programs for Bronze Rhapsody, an annual performance series choreographed, staged, and directed by Davenport. Her personal copy of a typescript of stage directions for a 1934 performance is included with these programs. Her dance schools, Davenport School of the Dance and Silver Box Studio, are documented in course brochures and applications. Biographical and academic materials include a 1939 newspaper article on Davenport.
Important Information for Users of the Collection
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired, 1998.
Biography
Mildred Ellen Davenport was a noted civic official and military officer with an extensive career as a dancer and dance instructor in Boston in the 1930s and 1940s. She was born in Boston on November 12, 1900. She began her dance studies at C.C. Perkins Grade School and Prince School as a teenager, and graduated from Boston Girls' High School in 1918. In the 1920s she studied at the Sargent School for Physical Culture and at Harvard, and opened her first dance school, the Davenport School of Dance. Over the next ten years she studied under Ted Shawn and taught dance in Boston. She was also progressively more involved in road show performances such as Hot Chocolates. From 1930 to 1935 she performed in a number of African-American musical productions on Broadway, including Fast and Furious, Flying Colors, and Black Birds. In 1932 she established her second dance school, the Silver Box Studio, in the South End of Boston. She became the first African American woman to perform with the Arthur Fiedler Pops unit of the Boston Symphony Orchestra at this time.
During World War II, Davenport enlisted in the Army as a captain. She produced musical shows for military bases and later served as a special service officer, library officer, and advisor in the Office of Racial Affairs. In 1950, she served as an executive board member for the N.A.A.C.P. office in Boston. From 1947 to 1968 she worked for the Massachusetts Commission Against Discrimination, founded in 1944 to enforce fair employment practices. Davenport died in Boston in 1990.
Chronology
1900 Born in Boston.
Ca. 1914 Student at C.C. Perkins Grade School and Prince School.
1918 Graduates from Boston Girls' High School.
Ca. 1920s Establishes Davenport School of Dance in Boston.
1921 Student at Sargent School for Physical Culture.
1921-1922 Physical training instructor at Tuskegee Institute, Alabama.
1923 Student at Harvard Summer School.
1925-ca. 1930 Staff member with the Department of Public Welfare, Boston.
Ca. 1930-1935 Performs on Broadway.
1932 Establishes Silver Box Studio in Boston.
1946-1947 U.S. Army, civilian defense instructor.
1947 U.S. Army Office of Racial Affairs, assistant special service officer, library officer, and advisor.
1950 Executive board member of N.A.A.C.P., Boston. Member of Women's Service Club and League of Women for Community Service, Boston.
1947-1968 Staff member with the Massachusetts Commission Against Discrimination.
1973 Receives Sojourner Truth Award of the National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Boston and Vicinity Club.
1990 Dies in Boston.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
This collection comprises dance programs, dance school materials, photographs, and ephemera documenting the early career of the Boston-based African-American dancer, dance instructor, and civic official Mildred Davenport. The bulk of this collection consists of dance programs and dance school materials. The collection also contains 29 photographs of Davenport, her students in various performances, and friends or individual students. Dance programs from 1925 to 1942 feature her solo performances and group performances with her students. The collection includes a complete run of programs for Bronze Rhapsody, an annual performance series choreographed, staged, and directed by Davenport. Her personal copy of a typescript of stage directions for a 1934 performance is included with these programs. Her dance schools, Davenport School of the Dance and Silver Box Studio, are documented in course brochures and applications. Biographical and academic materials include a 1939 newspaper article on Davenport.
The collection is arranged topically. Materials are arranged chronologically within each topical grouping whenever possible.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Davenport, Mildred, 1900-1990--Archives.; Dance schools--Massachusetts--Boston-- Archival resources.; Dance--Archival resources.; Modern dance--United States--Archival resources.; Dance, Black--Archival resources.; African American dancers--Archival resources.
Genres and Forms of Materials
Dance programs.; Photographic prints.; Posters.
Occupations
Dancers.; Dance teachers.
Collection Contents
- Biographical and academic materials (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Boston Girls' High School, commencement program, 1918 (Box-folder FB-21: 1)
  - George Peabody College for Teachers, School of the Dance, schedule of courses offered by Ted Shawn, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - "Boston teacher called evangelist of the dance," newspaper clipping, 1939 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Dance programs (Box-folder 1: 2-4)
  - The Feast of Apollo, Brattle Hall, Massachusetts, 1925 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Mildred Davenport and her pupils, Brattle Hall, Massachusetts, 1928 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Recital of dance poems and songs, Allied Art Studio, Boston, 1928 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Mildred Davenport and Sepia Beauties in revue, Challengers Club, Boston, 1933 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Bronze rhapsody (Box-folder 1: 2-3)
    - 1934 (Box-folder 1: 2)
      - Typescript of stage directions, with holograph note "Miss Davenport (personal)" on first leaf, 1934 (Box-folder 1: 2)
    - 1935- 1941 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1942 (Box-folder 1: 3)
      - Hand-colored poster (partial), 1942 (Box-folder FB-21: 1)
  - Classic, John Hancock Hall, Boston, 1938 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Shadowland Ball Room performances, Boston, undated., 2 items. (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Dance school materials (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Davenport School of the Dance application, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Silver Box Studio (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Course brochures and applications, undated., 3 items. (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Event invitation and greeting card, 1939 and undated.; 2 items. (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Photographs (Box-folder 1: 6-11)
  - Personal (Box-folder 1: 6-7)
    - Prince School class, photographic print, 1914 (Box-folder FB-21: 1)
    - Teenage performances, undated., 5 items. (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Portraits, undated., 3 items. (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Performances by students (Box-folder 1: 8-10)
    - Piggilly wiggily, ca. 1942 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Top hat, ca. 1942 (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - Unidentified, undated., 15 items. (Box-folder 1: 8-10)
  - Other individuals (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Hall, Tom, 1930 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Purcell, Barbara, ca. 1942 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Stokes, Bernice, ca. 1942 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Roberts, Francine, ca. 1942 (Box-folder 1: 11)
Example 2: Minnesota Territorial Archives - Records of Territorial Governor Willis A. Gorman Example 2 describes a series of government records that has been minimally encoded. It uses the "combined"
model to emphasize the hierarchical nature of the archival description. terr06 MINNESOTA TERRITORIAL ARCHIVES. Territorial Governor: An Inventory of Territorial Governor Willis A. Gorman Finding aid prepared by Lydia Lucas. Finding aid encoded by Lyda Morehouse, July 17, 2002.
Series Records of territorial governor Willis A. Gorman,
1852-1857.
Minnesota Historical Society
Agency:Minnesota. Governor (1853-1857: Gorman).
Subject files, correspondence, appointments, pardon records, reports from territorial officers, requests for return of fugitives, and miscellany.
0.75 cu. ft. (23 folders in 2 partial boxes).
BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH OF GOVERNOR WILLIS A. GORMAN
Willis Arnold Gorman was born in Kentucky on January 12, 1816. His early career was as a lawyer and state legislator (Democrat) in Indiana. During the Mexican War he raised and commanded an Indiana rifle battalion and an infantry regiment, and subsequently was elected to two terms in the U.S. Congress. President Franklin Pierce appointed him Governor of Minnesota in May 13, 1853, and he served in that office until 1857. He was subsequently a delegate to the state constitutional convention (1857) and was elected to the first state legislature (1858).
At the outset of the Civil War he commanded the First Minnesota Infantry Volunteers (April-October, 1861) until his promotion to brigadier general. Following his discharge from military service in 1864, he practiced law in St. Paul in partnership with Cushman K. Davis. In 1869 he was appointed St. Paul city attorney, and held that office until his death on May 20, 1876.
Sources: Minnesota Biographies, pp. 267- 268; Minnesota in the Civil and Indian Wars, Vol. I, p. 14; William Watts Folwell, A History of Minnesota (St. Paul, rev. 1956), Vol. I, pp. 377-383; Theodore C. Blegen, Minnesota, A History of the State (1963), pp. 171, 240-242, 293.
SCOPE AND CONTENTS OF THE RECORDS
Subject files and correspondence of territorial governor Gorman. A large proportion relate to territorial officers' appointments and commissions. Letters received and sent address the following topics: concerns of federal civilian agencies, military and Indian affairs in general, the 1855 treaty with the Winnebago Indians, land sales, the Minnesota and Northwestern Railroad Company, and other territorial affairs. Also present are a legislative diary (Jan. 27-March 6, 1857), pardon records, petitions regarding local government organization, reports from territorial officers, and requests from other states for return of fugitives.
Gorman's governorship spanned a period of both tangible and speculative growth in the state's infrastructure and economy, with numerous railroads, educational institutions, and corporations being chartered, new counties established, new towns incorporated, and several Indian treaties ratified. The surviving records contain only sketchy information on these developments, and do not appear to contain any significant documentation on an abortive 1857 scheme to remove the state capital from St. Paul to St. Peter.
ARRANGEMENT OF THE RECORDS
Arranged alphabetically by topic; thereunder chronologically within each folder.
INDEX TERMS
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the catalog of the Minnesota Historical Society. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Topics:
Civil-military relations--Minnesota.; Extraditions--Minnesota.; Federal government--Minnesota.; Indians of North America—Government relations--1789-1869.; Land titles--Minnesota--Registration and transfer.; Pardons--Minnesota.; Winnebago Indians--Treaties.
Places:
Minnesota--Officials and employees--Selection and appointment.; Minnesota--Politics and government--1849-1858.
Persons:
Gorman, Willis Arnold, 1816-1876.
Organizations:
Minnesota Territory.
Types of Documents:
Diaries--Minnesota.; Petitions--Minnesota.; Proclamations--Minnesota.; Territorial records--Minnesota.
Accession Information:
Accession number(s): none; 2001-46
DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE RECORDS
Note to Researchers: To request materials, please note both the location and box numbers shown below.
- Appointments: Commission of Deeds, 1853-1857.; 1 folder. ([1])
  For each individual, may include any of the following: application, petition, recommendations, letter of resignation.
- Appointments: Counties, 1853-1857.; 1 folder.
  For each individual, may include any of the following: application, petition, recommendations, letter of resignation. Arranged alphabetically by county.
- Appointments: Notary Public, undated and 1853-1857.; 4 folders.
- Appointments: Territorial Offices, 1853-1857.
  May include any of the following: application, petition, recommendations, letter of resignation, for commissioner of emigration, librarian, superintendent of common schools, auditor, treasurer, building commissioner, supreme court reporter, militia, and land office.
- Commissions, 1855-1857.; 5 items.
  For notary public, justice of the peace, and building commissioner.
- Document Transmittals, Receipts, and Requests, 1853-1857.; 1 folder.
- Legislative Diary, 1, 1857.; 1 volume
  Fragmentary entries, January 27 - March 6, showing numbers and titles of bills.
- Letters Received: Federal Civilian Agencies, 18, 1853-1857.; 1 folder.
  Letters and circulars from federal civilian agencies, including the General Land Office, the Post Office Department, and the Treasury Department.
- Letters Received: Indian and Military Affairs, 1853-1857.; 1 folder. ([1])
  Letters, reports, and orders relating to Indian and military affairs, from the commanding officers at Fort Snelling and Fort Ridgely; from legislative district representatives about the Winnebago treaty, with a copy of Governor Gorman's reply (January 1854); and petitions and requests for defense against the Indians.
  Includes a letter written by Henry B. Smythe on behalf of the Winnebago Indians (8 Jan. 1856) requesting the transfer of $806 from tribal funds to the superintendent of the Winnebago School. It may refer to funds available to the tribe under the 1855 U.S. Treaty with the Winnebago; it is signed by many of the Winnebago signatories to that treaty.
- Letters Received: Land Sales, 1853-1857.; 9 items.
  Letters about land sales and occupancy.
- Letters Received: Other Territorial Affairs, 1853-1857.; 16 items.
  Letters from Senator Henry M. Rice and others about a variety of territorial affairs.
- Pardon Records, 1852-1857.; 21 items. ([2])
  Requests and petitions for pardons and commutations; governor's pardon; orders for release and related court records; letters for persons convicted and sentenced for various offenses, including murder, assault with intent to kill, assault and battery, simple assault, and resisting an officer; and letters asking for the release of an Indian hostage.
- Petitions, 1853-1855.; 10 items.
  Various requests and petitions for the establishment of election precincts in Portsmouth and the Sioux Agency, for the organization of local governments in Rice County and Steele County, for a town organization in Bangor, for a vigilance committee to suppress liquor traffic at Traverse des Sioux, and for a certification of election districts in Carver County.
- Proclamations, 1854-1855.; 2 items.
  Designating November 21, 1854, and November 20, 1855 as days of Thanksgiving.
- Records Relating to the Minnesota and Northwestern Railroad Company, 1854-1856.; 31 items.
  Bills, correspondence, and reports dealing with its incorporation and with the political maneuverings surrounding its proposed land grant.
- Reports: Board of Inspectors of the Territorial Prison, 1853-1856.; 1 folder. ([2])
  Reports that include activities of the board and minutes of board meetings.
- Reports: Commissioner of Emigration, 1854-1857.; 1 folder.
  Reports of activities, and financial reports including lists of expenditures and various receipts.
- Reports: Other Territorial Officers, 1853-1855.; 7 items.
  - - Agent to select university lands (December 12, 1855).
  - - Commissioner for the Crystal Palace Exhibition (1853, 1854).
  - - Superintendent of common schools (December 25, 1854).
  - - Territorial auditor (December 30, 1854; December 26, 1855).
- Requests for Return of Fugitives, 1854-1857.; 2 folders.
  Both to and from various states.